Guide to the William Jackson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Jackson papers
1782-1828
MS 783
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(1 box, 1 folio)
The papers consist of correspondence, memoranda, and miscellaneous items of William Jackson, a major in the American Revolution and later an active political figure. Most of the items in the papers are letters received by Jackson between 1782 and 1828. Also included are memoranda relating to payments for surviving officers of the Continental Army and an account of the surrender of Lord Cornwallis. Among the correspondents are John Quincy Adams, Alexander Garden, Joseph Hopkinson, Ebenezer Huntington, Benjamin Lincoln, Charles Pinckney, John Sergeant and George Washington.
Jackson, William, 1759-1828
Conditions Governing Access
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 210 instead of the originals.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Henry Kirschenbaum to Beinecke Rare Book Library; transferred to Manuscripts and Archives, 1976.
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collectionis also available on microfilm (407 frames on 1 reel, 35 mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM210.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Incoming Correspondence. II. Manuscripts in the Hand of William Jackson. III. Miscellaneous and Printed Items.
Scope and Contents
The William Jackson Papers consist of approximately 120 items, the majority of which are letters received by Jackson during the years 1782 to 1828. Jackson corresponded with a large number of eminent men, among them George Washington, Thomas Jefferson, John Quincy Adams, William Henry Harrison, Henry Knox, and Charles Pinckney. However, most of the correspondence is routine in nature, e.g., cover letters, acknowledgements, and thank-you notes. Many of the letters, especially those written in 1818 and 1819, relate to efforts by Jackson and the Society of the Cincinnati to obtain the promised half pay of the surviving officers of the Continental Army. The bulk of this correspondence consists of letters acknowledging the receipt of memorials on behalf of the surviving officers and notes from sympathetic congressmen deploring the failure of Congress to act speedily on the matter.
The only material in the papers relating to Jackson's role as secretary to the Constitutional Convention is a letter from John Quincy Adams dated October 16, 1818, in which Adams asked Jackson if he had any material relating to the Constitutional Convention in his possession. Jackson responded that when he left Philadelphia in 1787 he turned over any relevant materials to Washington.
Other material of note includes several letters from the First Marquess of Landsdown (William Petty) commenting on Anglo-American relations and expressing his admiration of George Washington, a manuscript in Jackson's hand of a memorial to Congress on behalf of the surviving officers of the Continental Army, and an account, also in Jackson's hand, of Col. John Lauren's version of the surrender of Cornwallis at Yorktown.
The William Jackson Papers were given to Yale University Library by Henry Kirschenbaum, Purchase, New York, 1976 June 3.
Biographical / Historical
William Jackson was born in Cumberland, England, on March 9, 1759. Orphaned in early youth, Jackson was brought to South Carolina where he was raised under the guardianship of Owen Roberts. During the Revolutionary War Jackson served in the First South Carolina Regiment and later as an aide to Major-General Benjamin Lincoln. He subsequently served as Assistant Secretary of War under Lincoln (1782-1783). In 1787 he was appointed secretary of the Constitutional Convention and in the following year was admitted to the Pennsylvania Bar. From 1789 to 1791 Jackson served as personal secretary to President Washington and in 1796 was appointed Surveyor of Customs at Philadelphia. After losing his customs post in 1801 Jackson founded and edited the Philadelphia Political and Commercial Register (1801-1817).
Among his other notable activities Jackson was secretary of the Society of the Cincinnati from 1800 to 1828 and in this capacity was appointed by the surviving officers of the Continental Army to obtain for them an equitable adjustment of their promised half pay.
Jackson died in Philadelphia on December 18, 1828. For further information on his career see the Dictionary of American Biography.
United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; United States -- Politics and government; Yorktown (Va.) -- Siege, 1781; Politicians; Soldiers; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848; Harrison, William Henry, 1773-1841; Jackson, William, 1759-1828; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Knox, Henry, 1750-1806; Lansdowne, William Petty, Marquis of, 1737-1805; Pinckney, Charles, 1757-1824; Washington, George, 1732-1799; Society of the Cincinnati
- INCOMING CORRESPONDENCE, 1782-1828; Series I; 0.5
  Scope and Contents
  Incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. Letters of a particular correspondent are organized chronologically.
  - Adams, John Quincy (1767-1848), 16 October 1818 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
    General
    With copies of two letters from Jackson to Adams: 19 and 21 October 1818
  - Beck, Paul, Jr., 20 May 1812 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Biddle, Clement (1740-1814), 17 November 1818 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
  - Biddle, James (1783-1848), 20 July 1813 (2p.), 29 August 1817 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
  - Bingham, William (1752-1804), 4 September 1789 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Blake, W., 7 March 1786 (1p.), 3 June 1786 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Bloomfield, Joseph (1753-1823), 4 February 1818 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
  - Burrows, W. W., 23 February 1800 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
  - Carrington, Edward, 10 October 1782 (3p.) (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - Clarkson, Matthew (1758-1825), 24 January 1785 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
  - Colquhoun, Patrick (1745-1820), 30 January 1784 (2p.), 1 March 1784 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Corbin, Francis, 3 January 1815 (3p.) (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - Cushman, Joshua (1761-1834), 15 April 1820 (3p.) (Box 1, Folder 13, Reel 1U)
  - Custis, George Washington Parke (1781-1857), No date, Sunday (1p.), No year, October 15 (3p.) (Box 1, Folder 14, Reel 1U)
  - Davis, S. B., 23 May 1815 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 15, Reel 1U)
  - Eustis, William (1753-1825), 14 August 1819 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 16, Reel 1U)
  - Finley, S. B. R., 4 November 1828 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 17, Reel 1U)
  - Forrest, Thomas, 17 April 1820 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 18, Reel 1U)
  - Forsyth, John (1780-1841), 28 January 1818 (3p.) (Box 1, Folder 19, Reel 1U)
  - Fuller, Timothy, 25 April 1820 (3p.) (Box 1, Folder 20, Reel 1U)
  - Garden, Alexander (1757-1829), Undated (4p.), 2 June 1818 (3p.), 12 June 1818 (2p.), 4 August 1818 (2p.), 6 August 1818 (2p.), 18 October 1819 (3p.), 1 May 1821 (3p.), 2 December 1825 (2p.), 19 October 1827 (2p.), 13 October 1828 (1p.). (Box 1, Folder 21, Reel 1U)
  - Gibbon, James, 20 August 1819 (3p.), 16 December 1819 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 22, Reel 1U)
  - Goldsborough, Robert Henry (1780-1836), 19 April 1818 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 23, Reel 1U)
  - Harper, Robert Goodloe (1765-1825), 14 March 1824 (2p.), 5 November 1824 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 24, Reel 1U)
  - Harrison, William Henry (1773-1841), 2 March 1819 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 25, Reel 1U)
  - Hamphill, Joseph (1770-1842), 17 April 1820 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 26, Reel 1U)
  - Henderson [Francis?], 16 February 1827 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 27, Reel 1U)
  - Hopkinson, Joseph, 14 July 1817 (2p.), 15 March 1818 (3p.), 1 March 1819 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 28, Reel 1U)
  - Howard, John E., 14 August 1817 (1p.), 4 August 1818 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 29, Reel 1U)
  - Huntington, Ebenezer (1754-1834), 2 March 1819 (2p.), 16 August 1819 (2p.), 17 November 1819 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 30, Reel 1U)
  - Hyrne, Edmund Massingberd (1748-1783), 1 December 1783 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 31, Reel 1U)
  - Jefferson, Thomas (1743-1826), 1 March 1800 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 32, Reel 1U)
  - Johnson, Richard Mentor (1781-1850), 2 March 1819 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 33, Reel 1U)
  - King, Rufus (1755-1827), 3 March 1819 (1p.), 29 November 1820 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 34, Reel 1U)
  - Knox, Henry (1750-1806), 11 December 1793 (5p.) (Box 1, Folder 35, Reel 1U)
  - Lansdowne, William Petty, 1st marquess of (1737-1805), 5 October 1793 (1p.), 31 July 1795 (2p.), 19 April 1796 (2p.), 5 March 1797 (4p.) (Box 1, Folder 36, Reel 1U)
  - Latimer, George (1750-1825), 6 April 1804 (1p.), 21 January 1819 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 37, Reel 1U)
  - Laurens, Henry, Jr., 1 May 1792 (3p.) (Box 1, Folder 38, Reel 1U)
  - Levy, Moses, 27 August 1818 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 39, Reel 1U)
  - Lincoln, Benjamin (1733-1810), 7 December 1799 (2p.), 10 August 1784 (2p.), 30 October 1783 (2p.), 26 March 1800 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 40, Reel 1U)
    (Plus a copy made by Jackson)
  - Livingston, Edward (1764-1836), 22 December 1785 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 41, Reel 1U)
  - Lyman, Daniel, 2 August 1818 (2p.), 5 September 1819 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 42, Reel 1U)
  - Meigs, (Henry 1783-1861?), 2 May 1820 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 43, Reel 1U)
  - Mercer, Charles Fenton (1778-1858), 2 March 1819 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 44, Reel 1U)
  - Monroe, J. J., 11 December 1818 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 45, Reel 1U)
  - Noailles, Emanuel Marie Louis, marquis de (1743-1822), Undated (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 46, Reel 1U)
  - Pinckney, Charles (1757-1824), 15 April 1820 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 47, Reel 1U)
  - Pinckney, Charles Cotesworth (1746-1825), No year September 24 (2p.), 15 May 1800 (2p.), 5 September 1812 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 48, Reel 1U)
  - Pinckney, Thomas (1750-1828), 23 September 1800 (1p.), 1 August 1817 (1p.), 17 September 1827 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 49, Reel 1U)
  - Platt, Richard, 14 November 1817 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 50, Reel 1U)
    - Enclosing two printed documents relating to the Society of the Cincinnati. (Box 1, Folder 50, Reel 1U)
  - Rawle, William (1759-1836), 24 August 1818 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 51, Reel 1U)
  - Reed, Philip (1760-1829), 3 March 1819 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 52, Reel 1U)
  - Rutledge, John, Jr. (1739-1800), 28 July 1786 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 53, Reel 1U)
  - Scott, Winfield (1786-1866), 8 July 1815 (3p.) (Box 1, Folder 54, Reel 1U)
  - Sergeant, John (1779-1852), 10 December 1817 (1p.), 4 March 1819 (1p.), 18 May 1828 (2p.). (Box 1, Folder 55, Reel 1U)
    10 December 1817 contains draft of Jackson's reply. (2p.)
  - Shippen, Thomas Lee, 19 August 1786 (3p.) (Box 1, Folder 56, Reel 1U)
  - Tilghman, William (1756-1827), 5 August 1819 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 57, Reel 1U)
    Signed also by John B. Gibson & Thomas Duncan
  - Varick, Richard (1753-1831), 14 July 1818 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 58, Reel 1U)
  - Washington, George (1732-1799) (Box 1, Folder 59, Reel 1U)
    - Copies of two letters to Jackson (the copies made by Jackson), 1 November 1783 (1p.), 26 December 1791 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 59, Reel 1U)
  - Williams, Otho Holland (1749-1794), 22 September 1783 (3p.), 16 February 1786 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 60, Reel 1U)
  - Willing, Thomas, [1800?] (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 61, Reel 1U)
    - Also a writ, signed by Willing and summoning several citizens of Philadelphia to appear before him and testify against 3 highway robbers. 12 April 1771. (Box 1, Folder 62, Reel 1U)
  - Wycombe, Lord, 29 September 1793 (Box 1, Folder 62, Reel 1U)
- MANUSCRIPTS IN THE HAND OF WILLIAM JACKSON, 1818, undated; Series II
  - Letter to Ebenezer Huntington, 30 June 1818 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 63, Reel 1U)
  - Other drafts of letters by Jackson
    General note
    See: John Quincy Adams, box 1, folder 1
    See: Gamaliel Bradford, box 1, folder 67
  - Excerpts from the Journals of Congress outlining the resolutions of Congress relating to the half pay for officers of the Revolutionary Army, 1818 (3p.) (Box 1, Folder 64, Reel 1U)
  - "To Major General La Fayette. The address of the citizens of Philadelphia in their collective capacity,", (1824?) (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 65, Reel 1U)
  - Account, with corrections, of Col. Laurens's account of the surrender of Lord Cornwallis, Undated (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 66, Reel 1U)
  - Memorial to Congress on behalf of the surviving officers of the Revolutionary Army, Undated (2p.) (Box 2, Reel 1U)
- MISCELLANEOUS AND PRINTED ITEMS, 1782-1824, undated; Series III
  - Bradford, Gamaliel, 10 September 1818 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 67, Reel 1U)
    - Letter to Horace Binney (Box 1, Folder 67, Reel 1U)
      - With a copy of Major Jackson's reply to Bradford, 15 September 1818 (1p.) (Box 1, Folder 67, Reel 1U)
  - Carroll, Charles, of Carrollton (1737-1832): Letter to Charles Carroll, Jr., 7 January 1805 (3p.) (Box 1, Folder 68, Reel 1U)
  - Davis, John: Bill to William Jackson, 1819 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 69, Reel 1U)
  - Harper, Robert Goodloe (1765-1825): Letter to President James Monroe, 5 November 1824 (2p.) (Box 1, Folder 70, Reel 1U)
  - Mifflin, Thomas (1744-1800): Letter to President John Adams, Undated [July 4?] (Box 1, Folder 71, Reel 1U)
  - Parker, Isaac (1768-1830): Letter to William Eustis Signed also by Charles Jackson and Samuel Putnam, 16 November 1819 (4p.) (Box 1, Folder 72, Reel 1U)
  - Society of the Cincinnati: Proceedings of the New Jersey Society relative to the half-pay of the surviving officers of the Revolutionary Army and adopting the resolutions of the Pennsylvania Society of the Cincinnati, 4 July 1818 (4p.) (Box 1, Folder 73, Reel 1U)
  - Goldsborough, Robert Henry, 1780-1836: In the Senate. Speech of Mr. Golds-borough upon the bill to provide for the surviving officers and soldiers of the revolutionary army [1818?] (Broadside) (Box 1, Folder 74, Reel 1U)
  - Jackson, William: Memorial to Congress on behalf of the surviving officers of the revolutionary army, [December 1819] (Pamphlet) (Box 1, Folder 75, Reel 1U)
  - Marriage license form, filled in, for Henry Ferguson and Mary Potts, 10 January 1782 (Box 1, Folder 76, Reel 1U)